Guide to the Stanford War Records, 1917-1945 SC.0019
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Stanford War Records,
1917-1945
SC.0019
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
11.5 Linear feet
Duniway, C. A.
McDowell, John E.
Scope and Contents Note:
These records pertain to Stanford University faculty and student participation in World Wars I and II. Included are papers regarding the establishment of ambulance units; personal narratives of servicemen and correspondence with those in the service; drafts of a Stanford war history by Dr. C. A. Duniway; records of each Stanford participant in the First World War; records regarding women in war work, the Student Army Training Corps, civil defense, and war courses; and photographs and memorabilia.
Arrangement note
The collection is arranged in three series. The records in Series 1 were collected during 1918-1919 by John E. McDowell, Alumni Secretary, with the assistance of Prof. Edgar E. Robinson. Mr. McDowell was particularly active in corresponding with military personnel. A Committee on War Information was to prepare a "War History of Stanford" from these materials, but nothing came of this effort. In 1936 interest in the war records was revived with the construction of Memorial Hall on the Stanford campus. Dr. C. A. Duniway, former professor of history, engaged in bringing the war records up to date; his collected materials make up Series 2. Although Prof. Duniway prepared a draft of Stanford's war history, it was never published. Series 3 consists of materials from varied sources pertaining to the campus war effort and Stanford personnel in the services during World War II.
Access Restrictions
None.
Acquisition Information:
These records were first given to Stanford University Libraries and then moved to the Hoover Library in 1941. In 1964 they were returned to the Stanford Libraries to become part of the Stanford University Archives.
Provenance:
Collected by John E. McDowell and Dr. C. A. Duniway, with additions from other sources.
- World War I Subject Files, 1917-1919
  - Ambulance Units. First Stanford Unit, organized Feb. 2, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Ambulance Units. Second Stanford Unit, organized April 25, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Ambulance Units. Third Stanford Unit (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Ambulance Units. Fourth Stanford Unit (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Ambulance Units. Fifth Stanford Unit. Italian Ambulance Unit, American Red Cross (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Ambulance Units. General literature (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - American University Union in Europe Registers (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Civil Service. California State Civil Service Commission Announcements. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Civil Service. California State Civil Service Commission Announcements. Correspondence (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Committee on Public Information, Washington, D.C. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Draft (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Engineer enlisted reserve corps. Aeronautical engineers, 472D engineers (Signal Corps) (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Faculty War Service Departmental Record (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Faculty War Service, Lists and General matters (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - U. S. Food Administration correspondence, bulletins, etc. (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - U. S. Food Administration, food conservation notes (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - U. S. Food Administration. Herbert Clark Hoover. (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - U. S. Fuel Administration. Publications and releases. (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - U. S. Food Administration Speeches of Dr. Ray Lyman Wilbur (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Liberty Loan Campaign - Third (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Marine Corps Reserve. Marine Reserve Flying Corps (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Medical Enlisted Reserve Corps (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Naval Reserve Flying Corps. Coast Defense Reserve. Engineer's and Technicians' jobs (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Officers' Training School (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Personal narratives of Stanford servicemen (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Personal narratives (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Birge Clark, "World War I Memoirs" (Box 2, Folder 26a)
  - Personnel (periodical). U. S. Adjutant General Committee on Classification of Personnel in the Army (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Radio Instruction (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - ROTC 2nd Presidio Camp (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Stanord Women's Unit (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Student Army Training Corps (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - War History, blank forms (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - War History, appeals for data (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - War History, correspondence and exemplary materials - other universities (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - War History, survey of materials on file. April 1918 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - War History, June 1, 1918 report and preliminary summary (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - War History, Aug. 10, 1918 summary of work; Sept. 24, 1918 supplementary report (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - War History, Aug. 15, 1919 report of E. E. Robinson (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - War History, Ambulance Units, list (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - War History, Civilian service, list (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - War History, "History of Stanford in the Great War," by E. E. Robinson (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - War History, decorated, list (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - War History, died in service, list (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - War History, enlisted Medical Reserve Corps (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - War History, Faculty, Civilian-military (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - War History, foreign military service (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - War History, misc. lists and registers (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - War History, Red Cross in uniform (Box 3, Folder 48)
  - War History, wounded (Box 3, Folder 49)
  - War Service Memorial Committee (committee of 50). Minutes, suggestions, news (Box 3, Folder 50)
  - War History, main military list (Box 3, Folder 51)
  - War History, Stanford School of Nurses (Box 3, Folder 52)
  - War History, U. S. Base Hospital #30 (Box 3, Folder 53)
  - War History, U. S. Navy Base Hospital (Box 3, Folder 54)
  - War History, Women in Service (Box 3, Folder 55)
  - War History, YMCA (in uniform) (Box 3, Folder 56)
  - War Service Credit (Box 3, Folder 57)
  - Women in war work (Box 3, Folder 58)
  - Committee on War Information (Box 4, Folder 59)
  - War Service Memoral Fund (Box 4, Folder 60)
  - Women - position in war work (Box 4, Folder 61)
  - YMCA (Box 4, Folder 62)
  - Alan Nichols, copies of letters from France, 1918 (Box 4, Folder 63)
  - War Memorial, World War I (General Secretary's Office) (Box 4, Folder 63a)
- World War I Materials Collected by Dr. C. A. Duniway, 1937-1938
  - American Field Service in France (Box 5, Folder 64)
  - Camp Fremont (Box 5, Folder 65)
  - Clippings and copies of the Stanford Illustrated Review concerning Stanford in the war (Box 5, Folder 66)
  - Duniway, "War History of Stanford" (Box 5, Folder 67)
  - Memorial Building (Box 5, Folder 68)
  - Military Training Committee (Box 5, Folder 69)
  - Misc. printed items (Box 5, Folder 70)
  - Stanford Belgian Relief (Box 5, Folder 71)
  - Stanford School of Nursing War histories (Box 5, Folder 72)
  - Stanford war history chronology (Box 5, Folder 73)
  - Stanford war records, index of materials, 1936 (Box 5, Folder 74)
  - Stanford YMCA 1914-1918 (Box 5, Folder 75)
  - Student Army Training Corp. War issues course (Box 5, Folder 76)
  - War History, fraternities (Box 5, Folder 77)
  - War History, sororities (Box 5, Folder 78)
  - Biographical files of service men and women: A (Box 6, Folder 79-80)
  - Biographical files of service men and women: B (Box 6, Folder 81-83)
  - Biographical files of service men and women: C - Carl (Box 7, Folder 84-88)
  - Biographical files of service men and women: Carr - Cron (Box 8, Folder 89-92)
  - Biographical files of service men and women: Croo - En (Box 9, Folder 93-98)
  - Biographical files of service men and women: En - Gl (Box 10, Folder 99-103)
  - Biographical files of service men and women: Go - Hoe (Box 11, Folder 104-108)
  - Biographical files of service men and women: Hof - Kle (Box 12, Folder 109-115)
  - Biographical files of service men and women: Kli - MacD (Box 13, Folder 116-121)
  - Biographical files of service men and women: MacR - Or (Box 14, Folder 122-128)
  - Biographical files of service men and women: Os - Re (Box 15, Folder 129-134)
  - Biographical files of service men and women: Rho - Si (Box 16, Folder 135-141)
  - Biographical files of service men and women: Sk - Ti (Box 17, Folder 142-148)
  - Biographical files of service men and women: To - Will (Box 18, Folder 149-156)
  - Biographical files of service men and women: Wills - Z (Box 19, Folder 157-159)
  - Stanford War Record. Alumni Military Service List (Box 19, Folder 160-161)
  - Service with Allies (Box 19, Folder 162)
  - Faculty war records (Box 19, Folder 163)
  - Pro Patria Mortui (died in service) (Box 20, Folder 164-165)
  - Photographs of those who died in service (Box 20, Folder 166)
  - Biographical sketches of those who died in service (Box 20, Folder 167-168)
  - Book, the Story of the First Flag (Box 21, Folder 169)
  - Photo album, Ambulance Unit in the Balkans (Box 21, Folder 170)
  - Box of plates used in printing pictures of servicemen (Box 21, Folder 172)
- World War II Records, 1941-1945
  - News releases about Stanford (Box 21, Folder 173-174)
  - 1942 maps catalog prepared by O. S. S. and Military Intelligence (Box 21, Folder 175)
  - Dibble General Hospital - A History (Box 21, Folder 176)
  - American Field Service (Box 22, Folder 177)
  - Civil Affairs Training School (Box 22, Folder 178)
  - Civil Defense (Box 22, Folder 179)
  - Civil Defense, disaster preparedness and relief plan (Box 22, Folder 180)
  - Civil Defense (Box 22, Folder 181)
  - Committee on University Services (Box 22, Folder 182)
  - Engineering Science and Management War Training Program (Box 22, Folder 183)
  - War News (Box 22, Folder 184)
  - Miscellaneous printed matter pertaining to campus war effort, 1941-1945 (Box 22, Folder 185)
  - Letters from servicemen in response to President Donald B. Tresidder's letter inquiring about their post-war plans and their thoughts about Stanford University (Box 23, Folder 186-193)
  - War Memorial, World War II (General Secretary's Office) (Box 23, Folder 194)
  - Letters from Stanford men in service during World War II to Prof. Thomas Barclay (Box 23, Folder 195)